A Guide to the J. Rives Childs Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
J. Rives Childs Papers 1798-1973
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9256-g
This collection consists of ca. 2500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired on April 15, 1974 as a gift from Mr. Childs.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the J. Rives Childs collection consists of general and Casanova related correspondence, numerous photographs of his Near East consular activities and personal photographs, as well as a variety of miscellaneous material such as newspaper clippings, printed material, family pedigrees, diaries and scrapbooks. Of special note are a United States map of 1820 and a xerox copy of a signed letter by Casanova dated April, 1798.
Arrangement
This collection is filed according to subject.
Contents List
- General Correspondence 1905-1967 (Box 1)
  33 items
- General Correspondence 1968 (Box 1)
  150 items
- General Correspondence 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  311 items, 3 folders
- General Correspondence n.d. (Box 1)
  16 items
- General Correspondence re Casanova scholarship 1960-1973, n.d. (Box 1)
  3 folders
- Letter by Casanova 1798 Apr (Box 2)
  ALS (copy)
- Casanova material 20 c (Box 2)
  10 items
- Casanova research notes in French n.d. (Box 2)
  200 p.
- Casanova research notes in French n.d. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and magazine articles 20 c. (Box 2)
  50 items
- Miscellaneous printed material 20 c. (Box 2)
  30 items
- Documents re: Georgina Childs' death, and copy of Mathilde de Brylkine's will ca. 1969 (Box 2)
  6 items
- Miscellaneous materials in Russian 1889-1917 (Box 2)
  9 items
- Photographs re Jidda, Saudia Arabia ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
  18 items
- Photographs with Shiek Yussef Yassin ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
  14 items
- Photographs re consular activities 1939-1945 (Box 3)
  90 items
- Photographs re consular activities n.d. (Box 3)
  125 items
- Photographs re American Legation, Tangier, Morocco ca. 1941-1945 (Box 3)
  7 items
- Photographs re route Tahizz to Mahrib, Yemen ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
- Photographs re City of Aden, Aden airfield ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
  8 items
- Photographs re Mahrib irrigation project, Yemen ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
  25 items
- Photographs re City of Tahizz, Tahizz airfield, Yemen ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
- Photographs re City of Sada, Yemen ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
  3 items
- Phographs and map re City of Mahrib, Mahrib Territory, Yemen ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
- Photographs re Perim Island and Airfield, Bab El Mandeb ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
- Photographs re Childs' visit to [?] with Emperor Haile Selassie and John Humband, Director of Imperial Highway Authority 1952 (Box 3)
  15 items
- Photographs re route Aden to Tahizz, Yemen ca. 1939-1945 (Box 3)
  13 items
- Photographs of Childs' U.S. Tour 1949 (Box 3)
  75 items
- Photographs of Childs' U.S. Tour 1949 (Box 4)
  100 items
- Photographs re Felde's wedding (Georgina Childs' godchild, Mrs. Catesby Jones) n.d. (Box 4)
  5 items
- Miscellaneous photographs n.d. (Box 4)
  350 items, 2 folders
- Christmas cards wtih photographs 20th century (Box 4)
- Engravings of Rev. John Early and Elizabeth B. Early; sketches of Mr. and Mrs. Childs 1943, n.d. (Box 4)
  4 items
- Miscellaneous photographs n.d. (Box 5)
  150 items, 2 folders
- Pedigree of Rives of Virginia n.d. (Box 5)
- Brochure of "The Cliff," Georgina Childs' school in England ca. 1905 (Box 5)
  1 item
- Invitations 20th century (Box 5)
  28 items
- Miscellaneous currency n.d. (Box 5)
  80 items
- Passports and visas 20th century (Box 6)
  25 items, 3 folders
- Itinerary of motor journey in Iran 1934 or 1935 (Box 6)
- Cards wtih woodcuts by Eliezer Canul n.d. (Box 6)
- U.S. map 1820 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous 20th century (Box 6)
  130 items
- J. R. Childs' diaries 1921-1923 (Box 7)
  2 items
- Photo album of Georgina Childs ca. 1905-1923 (Box 7)
- Photo album of Georgina Childs ca. 1910 (Box 7)
  1 items
- Scrapbook of Georgina Childs as a young girl in Russia, Dresden, and England n.d. (Box 7)
- J. R. Childs' appointment books 1952-1963 (Box 7)
- Oversized Folio
  - Certificate of Distinction from Lynchburg Public High School to Lucy H. Brown 1873 June 30
  - 3 Diplomas of Lucy H. Brown from Lynchburg Public High School 1874 June 26
  - Diploma of John Wesley Childs from Lynchburg Public High School 1910 June 13
  - Childs' M.A. diploma from Harvard 1915 June 24
  - Certificate of thanks to America for the Refugee Kitchin Wassiti Ostroff, Petrograd 1922 Aug 22
  - Certificate of thanks to America for the Orphan Children's Relief Station 1922
  - Certificate of thanks to America for the Orphan Children's Home 1923 Feb
  - Certificate of Childs' appointment to Consul, class 7 1923 Oct 6
  - Certificate of Childs' appointment to Foreign Service Officer, class 8 1924 Jul 1
  - Certificate of Childs' appointment to Foreign Service Officer, class 8 1924 Dec 20
  - Membership certificate of Mrs. Lucy Brown Childs to the Daughters of the American Revolution 1925 Apr 16
  - Certificate appointing Childs consul to Bucharest, Rumania 1925 May 4
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 7 1929 May 23
  - Certificate appointing Childs Secretary in the Diplomatic Service 1930 Feb 17
  - Certificate appointing Childs consul to Cairo, Egypt 1930 Oct 1
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 6 1931 Dec 17
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 5 1935 Oct 1
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 5 1936 Jan 18
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 4 1939 Nov 16
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 4 1940 Jan 13
  - Certificate appointing Childs consul to Tangier, Morocco 1940 Dec 23
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 3 1942 Feb 20
  - Certificate appointing Childs Consul General 1944 Apr 25
  - Certificate appointing Childs Foreign Service Officer, class 1 1946 Feb 1
  - Certificate appointing Childs Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Saudi Arabia 1946 Apr 27
  - Certificate awarding honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters to Childs from Randolph-Macon College 1955 Feb 3
  - Certificate from Ordre de Chevaliers Ju vieux Moulin honoring Childs 1959 Jan 24
  - Certificate of Childs' membership in La Confrerie des Chevaliers du Tasteuin 1961 Jun 17
  - Certificate to Childs expressing thanks from Petersburg, Russia Deaf and Dumb Institution n.d.
  - Photograph of Childs n.d.
  - Photograph of King Ibn Saud of Saudi Arabia n.d.